northerntrust.com 2003-06-21

# Consumer Privacy Principles

Consumer Privacy Notice

Privacy at Northern Trust - Keeping Your Finances a Private Matter

When it comes to your financial affairs, you expect a relationship built on privacy and integrity. You can trust Northern to meet and exceed these expectations. 

We respect the premium you place on keeping your personal finances a private matter. **That’s why Northern Trust does not sell client lists or any other client information to outside companies.**

This notice outlines what we do to protect your personal information and describes how you can limit the sharing of certain information with our affiliated financial institutions. **If you already have instructed us not to share this information, you do not need to do anything**. We will continue to honor your request.

Keeping Your Information Secure   
Northern Trust employees must uphold a high standard of conduct to maintain our clients’ privacy. Preserving your trust is one of our core values. To keep information confidential and appropriately protected, we have policies that limit access to your personal information to only those employees who need it to perform their jobs and provide services to you. We also maintain physical, electronic, and procedural safeguards that comply with federal standards to guard your personal information.

Collecting Information   
Northern works hard to provide you with better service, better products, and a better financial relationship, and collecting information from our clients helps us do that. The types of information we collect are: 

  * Information you provide us on applications, forms, through our web sites, and in conversations 
  * Information we receive from third parties with your permission 
  * Information about your transactions with us or our affiliates 
  * Information we receive from consumer reporting agencies 

Sharing Information   
Only under certain circumstances, and only as permitted by law, will we disclose any of this information about our clients and former clients to unaffiliated third parties. For instance, we share with companies that perform services for us, such as a company that mails your statements or performs marketing services for us. These companies are not allowed to use this information to sell their products to you directly, and they are not allowed to sell this information to other companies. 

We also may share information with other affiliated and non-affiliated financial institutions with which we have joint marketing agreements. Some of these companies may include Northern Funds and the institution that provides and services Northern Trust credit cards. 

In addition, we share information we collect about our clients and former clients with our affiliated financial institutions — such as a Northern Trust Bank in another state and our securities broker-dealer, Northern Trust Securities, Inc. (NTSI). 

Benefits of Sharing Information    
Sharing information with our affiliated financial institutions enables us to evaluate your complete Northern Trust relationship so we may inform you of products and services that could be of value to you. It also allows us to invite you to special events we host for the benefit of our clients. 

Your Privacy Preferences   
Northern respects your right to restrict some of the information we disclose to our affiliates for marketing purposes. You may direct us not to share certain information such as your assets, income, date of birth, and information obtained through our account aggregation service by: 

  * Calling 1-866-260-9550, Monday through Friday, 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. Central Time 
  * Writing to us at Northern Trust, P.O. Box 92929, Chicago, IL 60675
  * Or stopping in one of our locations 

Please be sure to provide your full name, address, telephone number, and Social Security number. Your request will be processed within a reasonable period of time – please be aware that between the time you make the request and when it becomes effective, you still may receive marketing materials from an affiliate. 

If you have a joint account or have a guarantor of your account at Northern, we will assume your request applies only to your information, unless you tell us otherwise. If you contact us on behalf of a joint account holder or guarantor who wants to restrict the information we share, please be prepared to provide their full name, address, telephone number, and Social Security number as well.

Please note that even if you ask us not to share certain information with our affiliates for marketing purposes, we still may share that information for other reasons, such as to service your existing accounts. In addition, the Northern affiliate that originally collected the information still may use it for its own marketing decisions.

Keeping You Informed   
While this privacy statement will be provided to you annually, you only need to notify us once if you choose to restrict how we share information. If our information-sharing practices change, we will send you a revised notice. You also can return to this page on our web site, to view the most current privacy notice.

This privacy notice applies to all the Northern Trust affiliates listed below. If you have multiple accounts with Northern Trust or another affiliate, you may receive more than one privacy notice from Northern.

  * The Northern Trust Company* 
  * Northern Trust Securities, Inc. 
  * Northern Trust Bank, N.A.* 
  * Northern Trust Bank of California N.A.* 
  * Northern Trust Bank of Florida N.A.* 
  * Northern Trust Bank of Texas N.A.* 
  * Northern Trust Bank, FSB* 
  * The Northern Trust Company of Connecticut 
  * The Northern Trust Company of New York
  * Northern Trust Investments, Inc. 
  * Northern Trust Global Advisors, Inc. 
  * Northern Trust Global Investments (Europe) Limited 

*Member FDIC 

How to Reduce Direct Marketing from Other Companies

If you want to reduce the amount of direct marketing you receive from companies other than Northern Trust or our affiliates, you can write to the following agencies (be sure to include complete information on each name, address, and telephone number you’d like excluded from these lists): 

> For materials received by mail:  
>  Mail Preference Service  
>  Direct Marketing Association  
>  P.O. Box 9008  
>  Farmingdale, NY 11735-9008 
> 
> For phone solicitations:  
>  Telephone Preference Service  
>  Direct Marketing Association  
>  P.O. Box 9014  
>  Farmingdale, NY 11735-9014 
> 
> For e-mail solicitations:  
>  E-mail Preference Service  
>  www.e-mps.org 

Also, you can have your name taken off pre-approved credit solicitations by writing to the following credit reporting bureaus or calling 1-888-5OPTOUT (1-888-567-8688). Be sure to include your name, address, Social Security number, date of birth, and telephone number. 

> Experian Consumer Opt Out  
>  901 West Bond Street  
>  Lincoln, NE 68521  
>  or call 1-800-407-1088 (please specify if you want your name removed from mailing lists or telemarketing lists) 
> 
> Equifax Options  
>  P.O. Box 740123  
>  Atlanta, GA 30374-0123 
> 
> Trans Union LLC’s Name Removal Option  
>  P.O. Box 97328  
>  Jackson, MS 39288-7328
